I was 14 years old
كان عمري 14 عاماً
inside of a bowling alley,
داخل مركز بولينج،
burglarizing an arcade game,
كنت أسرق نقود لعبة أركاد
and upon exiting the building
وقبل الخروج من المبنى
a security guard grabbed my arm, so I ran.
أمسك حارس الأمن ذراعي، فجريت.
I ran down the street, and I jumped on top of a fence.
جريت إلى الشارع، وقفزت إلى أعلى سياج حديدي
And when I got to the top,
وعندما وصلت إلى الأعلى،
the weight of 3,000 quarters in my book bag
جذبتني حقيبتي الحاوية على ثلاث آلاف عملة نقدية
pulled me back down to the ground.
وطرحتني أرضاً.
So when I came to, the security guard was standing on top of me,
وعندما وقفت كان حارس الأمن يقف فوقي
and he said, "Next time you little punks steal something you can carry."
وقال "في المرة القادمة ااسرقوا شيئاً يمكنكم حمله أيها الأوغاد الصغار. "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was taken to juvenile hall
اُخِذت إلى سجن الأحداث
and when I was released into the custody of my mother,
وعندما أطلِقَ سراحي تحت وصاية أمي،
the first words my uncle said was, "How'd you get caught?"
كان أول شيء قاله عمي: "كيف أمسكوا بك ؟"
I said, "Man, the book bag was too heavy."
قلت: "كانت حقيبة الكتاب ثقيلة للغاية يا رجل"
He said, "Man, you weren't supposed to take all the quarters."
فقال: "لم يكن من المفترض أن تسرق كل الأرباع المعدنية."
I said, "Man, they were small. What am I supposed to do?"
قلت: "لقد كان حجمهم صغيراً يا رجل، ماذا كان علي أن أفعل؟"
And 10 minutes later, he took me to burglarize another arcade game.
بعدها بعشر دقائق، أخذني لنسرق لعبة أركاد أخرى.
We needed gas money to get home.
احتجنا توفير ثمن عودتنا للمنزل.
That was my life.
هكذا كانت حياتي
I grew up in Oakland, California,
نشأت في أوكلاند، كاليفورنيا،
with my mother and members of my immediate family
مع أمي وأفراد أسرتي
addicted to crack cocaine.
المدمنين على الكوكايين.
My environment consisted of living with family, friends,
تتكون بيئتي من الذين يعيشون مع العائلة والأصدقاء،
and homeless shelters.
ومأوى المشردين.
Oftentimes, dinner was served in breadlines and soup kitchens.
في أغلب الأحيان، كان العشاء يتكون من خبز وحساء.
The big homey told me this:
وأخبرني رفيقي العزيز
money rules the world
أن المال يحكم العالم
and everything in it.
بكل ما فيه.
And in these streets, money is king.
وفى هذه الشوارع، يُعد المال هو الملك.
And if you follow the money,
وإذا جريت وراء المال،
it'll lead you to the bad guy or the good guy.
سيقودك إما إلى الرجل السيء أو الرجل الصالح
Soon after, I committed my first crime,
وبعدها بفترة قصيرة، ارتكبت جريمتى الأولى،
and it was the first time that I was told that I had potential
وكانت المرة الأولى التي يُقال لي فيها أن لدي إمكانيات
and felt like somebody believed in me.
وشعرت بأن هناك من يؤمن بي.
Nobody ever told me that I could be a lawyer,
لم يخبرنى أحد من قبل أنه يمكن أن أصبح محاميًا،
doctor or engineer.
طبيبًا أو مهندسًا.
I mean, how was I supposed to do that? I couldn't read, write or spell.
ولكن كيف عساي أن أفعل ذلك؟ فأنا لا أعرف القراءة أو الكتابة أو التهجئة.
I was illiterate.
كنت أمياً.
So I always thought crime was my way to go.
لهذا كنت أعتقد أن الجريمة هي وسيلتي الوحيدة للعيش.
And then one day
وذات يوم
I was talking to somebody
كنت أتحدث إلى شخص ما
and he was telling me about this robbery that we could do.
فأخبرني عن عملية السرقة التي يمكن أن نقوم بها.
And we did it.
وقد قمنا بها.
The reality was that I was growing up
الحقيقة أنني كنت أترعرع
in the strongest financial nation in the world,
فى أقوى أمة اقتصادية فى العالم،
the United States of America,
الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
while I watched my mother stand in line at a blood bank
في الوقت الذي كنت أشاهد فيه أمي وهي تقف في الصف في بنك الدم
to sell her blood for 40 dollars just to try to feed her kids.
لكى تبيع دمها مقابل 40 دولاراً فقط لإطعام أولادها.
She still has the needle marks on her arms to day to show for that.
لا تزال وخزات الإبر موجودة في ذراعيها إلى اليوم لتشهد على ذلك
So I never cared about my community.
لذا لم أعبأ يوماً بمجتمعي.
They didn't care about my life.
فهم لم يعبأوا بحياتي.
Everybody there was doing what they were doing to take what they wanted,
الكل هناك كان يفعل ما يفعله ليأخذ ما يريد،
Everybody was taking blood money.
الكل كان يأخذ الدية.
So I got mine by any means necessary.
لذا حصلت على المال بأي طريقة ممكنة.
I got mine.
حصلت عليه.
Financial literacy really did rule the world,
فالوعي المالي يحكم العالم بالفعل،
and I was a child slave to it
وأنا كنت طفلاً عبداً له
following the bad guy.
تابعاً للشخص السيء.
At 17 years old, I was arrested for robbery and murder
فى سن السابعة عشر تم اعتقالي بتهمتي القتل والسرقة
and I soon learned that finances in prison rule more than they did on the streets,
وعرفت بعدها أن حكم الماديات في السجن أكثر منه في الشوارع،
so I wanted in.
لذا أردته.
One day, I rushed to grab the sports page of the newspaper
ذات يوم اندفعت لأحصل على صفحة الرياضة من الجريدة
so my cellie could read it to me,
ليقرأها لي رفيقي في الزنزانة،
and I accidentally picked up the business section.
ولكني بالخطأ أخذت صفحة الأعمال
And this old man said, "Hey youngster, you pick stocks?"
فقال لى الرجل العجوز: "أيها الفتى، أتتابع البورصة؟"
And I said, "What's that?"
فقلت: "وماذا تكون هذه؟"
He said, "That's the place where white folks keep all their money."
قال: "إنها ذلك المكان الذي يضع فيه الأناس البيض كل أموالهم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it was the first time that I saw a glimpse of hope,
وكانت تلك المرة الأولى التي أرى فيها بصيصاً من الأمل
a future.
مستقبل.
He gave me this brief description of what stocks were,
لقد أعطاني تعريفاً مختصراً عن البورصة،
but it was just a glimpse.
ولكنه كان مجرد بصيص.
I mean, how was I supposed to do it?
أقصد، كيف يمكنني أن أفعلها؟
I couldn't read, write or spell.
كنت أجهل القراءة أو الكتابة أو التهجئة.
The skills that I had developed to hide my illiteracy
فالمهارات التي طورتها لأخفي أميتي
no longer worked in this environment.
لم تعد صالحة فى هذه البيئة.
I was trapped in a cage, prey among predators,
كنت محبوساً فى قفص، فريسة فى وسط مفترسين،
fighting for freedom I never had.
أقاتل من أجل حرية لم أحظ بها يوماً.
I was lost, tired,
كنت تائهاً، ومتعباً،
and I was out of options.
وقد نفذت لدي الخيارات.
So at 20 years old,
لذلك وفي عمر العشرين،
I did the hardest thing I'd ever done in my life.
فعلت أصعب شيء يمكن أن أقوم به فى حياتي.
I picked up a book,
أخذتُ كتاباً،
and it was the most agonizing time of my life,
وكان أكثر أوقات حياتي ألماً،
trying to learn how to read,
أن أتعلم كيف أقرأ،
the ostracizing from my family,
نبذي من عائلتى،
the homeys.
والرفاق،
It was rough, man.
لقد كان صعباً يا رجل.
It was a struggle.
كانت معاناة.
But little did I know
وكلما عرفت القليل
I was receiving the greatest gifts I had ever dreamed of:
كنت أكتسب أعظم الهبات التي لم أكن أحلم بها يوماً:
self-worth,
قيمة الذات،
knowledge, discipline.
المعرفة والإلتزام.
I was so excited to be reading that I read everything I could get my hands on:
كنت متحمساً للقراءة حتى أنني كنت أقرأ كل ما تصل إليه يدى:
candy wrappers, clothing logos, street signs, everything.
أغلفة الحلوى، شِعارات الملابس، لافتات الشوارع، كل شيء.
I was just reading stuff!
كنت فقط أقرأ أشياء!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Just reading stuff.
فقط أقرأ.
I was so excited to know how to read and know how to spell.
كنت متحمسًا جدًا لمعرفة كيفية القراءة والتهجئة.
The homey came up, said, "Man, what you eating?"
أتى ذلك الرفيق مرة وقال: "يا رجل ماذا تأكل؟"
I said, "C-A-N-D-Y, candy."
قلت: "ح-ل-و-ى، حلوى."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He said, "Let me get some." I said, "N-O. No."
فقال: "أعطني بعضاً منها" قلت: "ل-ا، لا"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was awesome.
كان ذلك رائعاً.
I mean, I can actually now for the first time in my life read.
أقصد أنني أستطيع الآن ولأول مرة فى حياتى في حياتي أن اقرأ.
The feeling that I got from it was amazing.
والشعور الذي راودني حيال ذلك كان رائعاً.
And then at 22, feeling myself,
وفى سن الـ22، شَعرتُ بنفسي،
feeling confident,
وشَعرتُ بالثقة،
I remembered what the OG told me.
ثم تذكرت ما قاله لي رجل العصابة.
So I picked up the business section of the newspaper.
لذا التقطت صفحة الأعمال من الجريدة
I wanted to find these rich white folks.
لأني أردت أن أجد هؤلاء الأناس البيض الأغنياء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I looked for that glimpse.
فأخذت أبحث عن هذا البصيص من الأمل.
As I furthered my career
وعندما تقدمت بمهنتي
in teaching others how to financially manage money and invest,
وهي تعليم الآخرين كيفية إدارة أموالهم وكيفية الاستثمار،
I soon learned that I had to take responsibility for my own actions.
سرعان ما تعلمت أنه يجب علي أن أتحمل مسؤولية أفعالي.
True, I grew up in a very complex environment,
صحيح، أنا ترعرعت في بيئة معقدة جدًا،
but I chose to commit crimes,
ولكنني اخترت أن أرتكب الجرائم،
and I had to own up to that.
كان علي أن أعترف بذلك.
I had to take responsibility for that, and I did.
كان علي أن أتحمل مسؤولية هذا وبالفعل تحملتها.
I was building a curriculum that could teach incarcerated men
كنت أصمم منهاجًا يمكنه أن يُعلم المسجونين
how to manage money through prison employments.
كيفية إدارة أموالهم من خلال عملهم في السجن.
Properly managing our lifestyle would provide transferrable tools
فإدارة أسلوب حياتنا كما ينبغي سيوفر لنا أدوات قابلة للنقل والتحويل
that we can use to manage money when we reenter society,
يمكننا أن نستخدمها في إدارة المال عندما نعود لمجتمعنا،
like the majority of people did who didn't commit crimes.
كما فعل أغلبية الناس الذين لم يرتكبوا جرائم.
Then I discovered
وبعدها اكتشفت
that according to MarketWatch,
أنه وفقا لموقع "ماركت ووتش"،
over 60 percent of the American population
أن أكثر من 60% من الأمريكيين
has under 1,000 dollars in savings.
لديهم أقل من 1,000 دولار في مدخراتهم.
Sports Illustrated said that over 60 percent of NBA players
كما أوضحت مجلة "سبورتس السترايتد" أن 60 % من لاعبي" ان بي ايه"
and NFL players go broke.
ولاعبي"ان اف ال"
40 percent of marital problems derive from financial issues.
تحدث مشكلاتهم الزوجية بنسبة 40 % بسبب المشكلات المادية.
What the hell?
ما هذا بحق الجحيم؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You mean to tell me that people worked their whole lives,
أتقصد أن الناس الذين عملوا طوال حياتهم،
buying cars, clothes, homes and material stuff
واشتروا السيارات والملابس والمنازل و الأشياء
but were living check to check?
كانوا يعيشون بالقليل من المال؟
How in the world were members of society going to help incarcerated individuals
كيف سيستطيع أبناء المجتمع مساعدة الأشخاص المسجونين
back into society
على العودة لمجتمعهم
if they couldn't manage they own stuff?
إن لم يستطيعوا هم إدارة شؤونهم الخاصة؟
We screwed.
نحن في ورطة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I needed a better plan.
أردت خطة أفضل
This is not going to work out too well.
فلن تعمل هذه بشكل جيد
So ...
لذا ...
I thought.
فَكرتُ.
I now had an obligation to meet those on the path
إنني الآن ملزم أن أقابل هؤلاء الذين يسلكون هذا الدرب
and help,
وأن أساعد،
and it was crazy because I now cared about my community.
وكان هذا تفكير جنوني فأنا الآن أهتم بمجتمعي.
Wow, imagine that. I cared about my community.
يا للهول، تخيل ذلك أنا اهتممت بمجتمعي.
Financial illiteracy is a disease
فالجهل بالأمور المالية هو وباء
that has crippled minorities and the lower class in our society
شلّ الأقليات والطبقة الفقيرة في مجتمعنا
for generations and generations,
لأجيال وأجيال،
and we should be furious about that.
وعلينا أن نكون غاضبين حيال هذا
Ask yourselves this:
اسأل نفسك هذا السؤال:
How can 50 percent of the American population
كيف يكون 50% من الأمريكيين
be financially illiterate in a nation driven by financial prosperity?
جاهلين ماليًا في أمة يقودها الرخاء المادي؟
Our access to justice, our social status,
مدخلنا للعدالة، أحوالنا الاجتماعية،
living conditions, transportation and food
الأحوال المعيشية، وسائل المواصلات والطعام
are all dependent on money that most people can't manage.
كل هذا يعتمد على المال الذي لا يستطيع الناس إدارته.
It's crazy!
إنه لجنون!
It's an epidemic
إنه وباء
and a bigger danger to public safety than any other issue.
وأكثر خطرًا على الأمن العام من أي قضية أخرى.
According to the California Department of Corrections,
ووففًا لإدارة السجون الخاصة بكاليفورنيا،
over 70 percent of those incarcerated
إن 70% من هؤلاء المسجونين
have committed or have been charged with money-related crimes:
ارتكبوا أو اتهموا بارتكاب جرائم ذات صلة بالأموال
robberies, burglaries, fraud, larceny, extortion --
سرقات، عمليات سطو احتيال، اختلاس، ابتزاز --
and the list goes on.
وتستمر القائمة،
Check this out:
تفقدوا هذا:
a typical incarcerated person
شخص عادي مسجون
would enter the California prison system
يدخل إلى سجن كاليفورنيا
with no financial education,
دون أي ثقافة مالية،
earn 30 cents an hour,
كسب 30 سنتًا في الساعة،
over 800 dollars a year,
وأكثر من 800 دولار في السنة،
with no real expenses and save no money.
دون أي إنفاق حقيقي ولا يدخر أي مال.
Upon his parole, he will be given 200 dollars gate money and told,
وحين يتم إطلاق سراحه، سيعطونه 200 دولار ويقولون له:
"Hey, good luck, stay out of trouble. Don't come back to prison."
"حظا سعيدًا، اِبق بعيدًا عن المشاكل ولا تأتي للسجن مرة أخرى."
With no meaningful preparation or long-term financial plan,
دون أي تحضيرات هادفة أو خطة مالية طويلة المدى،
what does he do ... ?
ماذا عليه أن يفعل...؟
At 60?
في سن الستين؟
Get a good job,
أيحصل على وظيفة جيدة،
or go back to the very criminal behavior that led him to prison in the first place?
أم يعود للسلوك الإجرامي الذي أودى به في المقام الأول إلى السجن؟
You taxpayers, you choose.
فيا دافع الضرائب، عليك أن تختار
Well, his education already chose for him, probably.
من المحتمل أن تعليمه قد اختار له بالفعل
So how do we cure this disease?
إذًا، كيف نُعالج هذا المرض؟
I cofounded a program
اشتركت في تأسيس برنامج
that we call Financial Empowerment Emotional Literacy.
نطلق عليه اسم" التمكين المالي الماحي للأمية العاطفية"
We call it FEEL,
حيث نطلق عليه" فييل"
and it teaches how do you separate your emotional decisions
وهو يعلمك كيف تفصل قراراتك العاطفية
from your financial decisions,
عن قراراتك المالية،
and the four timeless rules to personal finance:
والأربعة قواعد الأبدية للتمويل الشخصي هي:
the proper way to save,
اختيار أسلوب مناسب للادخار،
control your cost of living,
اضبط تكاليف معيشتك،
borrow money effectively
اقترض المال بكفاءة
and diversify your finances by allowing your money to work for you
ونوّع مواردك المالية عن طريق جعل المال يخدمك
instead of you working for it.
بدلاً من أن تخدمه أنت.
Incarcerated people need these life skills before we reenter society.
فالأشخاص المسجونون يحتاجون لهذه المهارات الحياتية قبل العودة للمجتمع.
You can't have full rehabilitation without these life skills.
فلن تحصل على إعادة تأهيل كاملة دون هذه المهارات الحياتية.
This idea that only professionals can invest and manage money
فالاعتقاد أن الخبراء وحدهم هم من يستطيعون استثمار وإدارة الأموال
is absolutely ridiculous,
هو قطعًا اعتقادٌ سخيف،
and whoever told you that is lying.
وأيا كان من قال لك ذلك فهو يكذب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
A professional is a person
الخبير هو الشخص
who knows his craft better than most,
الأدرى بمهنته أكثر من أي شخص آخر
and nobody knows how much money you need, have or want better than you,
ولا أحد يعرف كم من المال أنت تحتاجه، تملكه، تريده أكثر منك،
which means you are the professional.
وهذا يعني أنك أنت الخبير.
Financial literacy is not a skill, ladies and gentlemen.
الوعي المالي ليس مهارة، سيداتي وسادتي.
It's a lifestyle.
بل هو أسلوب حياة.
Financial stability is a byproduct of a proper lifestyle.
الاستقرار المالي يُعد حصيلة ثانوية لأسلوب حياة لائق.
A financially sound incarcerated person can become a taxpaying citizen,
فالشخص المسجون المستقر ماديًا يمكن أن يصبح مواطن دافع للضرائب،
and a financially sound taxpaying citizen can remain one.
ودافع الضرائب المستقر ماديًا يمكن أن يظل هكذا.
This allows us to create a bridge between those people who we influence:
وهذا يسمح لنا بأن نصنع جسرًا يربط بين هؤلاء الذين نؤثر فيهم:
family, friends and those young people
العائلة والأصدقاء والأشخاص الصغار
who still believe that crime and money are related.
الذين ما زالوا يعتقدون أن الجريمة والمال مترابطان.
So let's lose the fear and anxiety
دعونا نحذف الخوف والتوتر
of all the big financial words
من المصطلحات المادية الكبيرة
and all that other nonsense that you've been out there hearing.
وكل ذلك الهراء الآخر الذي تسمعونه في الخارج.
And let's get to the heart of what's been crippling our society
ودعونا نتوصل لجوهر ما يُعطلُ مجتمعنا
from taking care of your responsibility to be better life managers.
من تولي أمر مسؤوليتكم حتى تُصبحوا مدراء حياة أفضل.
And let's provide a simple and easy to use curriculum
ودعونا نقدم منهاجًا بسيطًا وسهل الاستخدام
that gets to the heart, the heart
بإمكانه أن يصل للجوهر،
of what financial empowerment and emotional literacy really is.
الجوهر الذي يعبر عن ماهية التمكين المادي ومحو الأمية العاطفية.
Now, if you're sitting out here in the audience and you said,
والآن، إن كنت تجلس هنا وسط الجمهور وقلت:
then come take my class --
فتعال احضر درسي --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
so I can show you how much money it costs you every time you get emotional.
حينها أستطيع أن أبين لك كم من المال تنفق حينما تصبح عاطفيًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you very much. Thank you.
شكرًا جزيلاً لكم، شكرًا.